ANDRII ABRAMOV

TEAM/TECH LEAD

SUMMARY

CTO / Tech Lead with 6+ years of professional expertise. I have experience in launching several successful projects from scratch and managing teams. I'm a development fanatic and I need really interesting projects. Engineering is the first of all my hobbies and then only my profession. I have a great understanding of business goals, I know how to balance between deadlines and quality. I understand when you need to do something really fast to get business value, and when you need to say "NO".

FinTech fan with experience in bootstrapping Payment Service Providers from scratch. Passionate about functional

programming, strongly typed languages, Kubernetes and Scala. I also like working with infrastructure and service

reliability: CI/CD, deployment, release management, monitoring, and metrics.



@abramov_andrii



abramov.andrii@gmail.com



LinkedIn | Github



StackOverflow | Blog

EDUCATION

National Technical University of Ukraine 'Kyiv Polytechnic Institute', Master's degree

SEPTEMBER 2014 - JUNE 2020

Faculty of Applied Maths

CERTIFICATIONS

Java SE 8 Programmer

Oracle Certified Professional,

Oracle Certified Associate, Java

Specialty: Software Engineering

WORK EXPERIENCE

Chief Technology Officer (CTO) - NDA

Sep 2021 - Present

Project

Development of electronic wallet systems from scratch. The project is mostly focused on B2C. The project is being launched under my leadership. The launch took place a month after I joined the project. During this time, the infrastructure was completely redone.

Client

Ukrainian startup.

Responsibilities

Technical:

- Designing project architecture
- Infrastructure management (GCP, Terraform, Helm, Cloudflare, Istio)
- Managing CI/CD infrastructure (CircleCI, Spinnaker, Helm)
- Production monitoring and responding to alerts
- Making releases

Non-technical:

- Team recruitment (from interview to onboarding)
- Performance review / 1-to-1
- · Project budgeting / Cost reporting

LANGUAGES

SE 8 Programmer

- English Advanced
- German Elementary
- · Ukrainian Native

<u>Achievements</u>

Led development team directly (5 team members). Launched the project from scratch in 1 month, instead of the agreed 3 months.

The results of the first month of my work were:

- Primary audit a bunch of code reviews and comments + fixes
- A security audit was conducted (both internally by me and externally through the contractor, a number of fixes were made before launch)
- The infrastructure for the project on Google Cloud is completely made from scratch with three environments: dev/stage/prod (DevOps)
- Set up CI/CD pipelines with CircleCI, Spinnaker, and Helm. Releases are being made with canary deployments and automated monitoring.
- Tripled back-office tool development by properly aggregating data sources.
- Raised two awesome middle engineers :)

Technology stack:

DevOps

- Google Cloud: Kubernetes Engine, SQL, Storage, CDN, Endpoints, Structured Logging
- <u>Infrastructure</u>: GCP, Terraform, Helm, Istio (Mesh, Ingress, Egress, Kiali), CircleCI, Spinnaker, Grafana, Prometheus, Cloudflare
- Messaging: RabbitMQ, NATS
- Databases: Cloud SQL (PostgreSQL), BigQuery, Elasticsearch
- Serverless: Google Cloud Functions, App Engine
- · Scripting: Bash, Python

Software Engineering

- In addition, from time to time, II am involved in services development using Scala/Node.js (NestJS / TS), usually the most critical cases, and technologies:
 - o Scala: ZIO / http4s / Cats / Doobie / Slick / Flyway / Refined
 - Node.js: TS / NestJS / TypeORM / MikroORM / ioredis / AMQP / winston
 - OpenAPI/Swagger

ANDRII ABRAMOV

TEAM/TECH LEAD

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer (Scala) - Exabeam

Sep 2020 - Sep 2021

Project

One of the largest companies in the world specializing in cyber security. Processing terabytes of streaming data collected on the client side, real-time enrichments and subsequent persistence in indexed storage.

Client

American private company www.exabeam.com

Responsibilities

- Developing data enrichment pipeline stage for real-time analytics
- Supporting several utility services
- Requirements collection
- Release management
- · Interviewing Scala candidates
- Stage / Production deployment
- · Documenting existing services and writing proposals for PoCs

Achievements

- Created several microservices for streaming data enrichment and further construction of aggregation real-time analytics.
 Integrated these services into the main pipeline for events enrichment
- Improved cache performance by a factor of 150 by flattening key trees
- · Developed fault-tolerant scheduler with leader election and time-zone support
- Implemented analytics wiretapper for calculating pipeline costs
- Implemented schema tracker for further validation and UI autocompletion
- Created dashboard and alerts for several pipelines
- · Added cache performance monitoring
- Wrote tons of documentation for PoCs and algorithmic proposals

Technology stack:

- Scala: Akka HTTP / Streams / Actors, cats, refined, pureconfig, enumeratum
- MongoDB
- Kafka / NATS
- Kubernetes
- · Docker / Jenkins
- Releases / monitoring / on-call duties

Team/Tech Lead - Tranzzo

Sep 2017 - Sep 2020

Project

Payment Service Provider development from scratch. Currently serves tens of thousands of customers globally.

Client

Ukrainian startup https://tranzzo.com/

Responsibilities

Technical:

- · Full software development cycle (requirements, design, development, testing, release, monitoring)
- Development of prototypes within R&D
- Release management (here the responsibility was mostly on the developers, not on one person)
- Support Staging / Production environments (GKE / Terraform / Helm)
- Development & support of CI/CD Pipelines

Non-technical:

- Full cycle of technical recruitment
- Performance review / 1-to-1 meetings
- Team performance reporting

ANDRII ABRAMOV

TEAM/TECH LEAD

WORK EXPERIENCE

Achievements

I joined the project at the planning stage as a Senior Software Engineer. After two weeks, we started development. I've been writing the first lines of code. A year later, I was offered to become a Team/Tech Lead (10 team members), because the team has already grown quite a bit. Almost two years later, when the team became even bigger (18 team members), I focused exclusively on the technical component of the project as a Tech Lead. At the same time, I conducted interviews/recruitment and team evaluation. The pilot project was launched 4 months after the start of development. Currently, the project serves more than 10,000 businesses and processes about 500,000 payments daily around the world.

I was involved in designing project architecture, including DevOps. Took part in the development of prototypes. Also responsible for monitoring and responding to incidents.

Technology stack:

- Languages: Scala, Java
- Google Cloud: Kubernetes Engine, SQL, Storage, PubSub, CDN, Endpoints, Structured Logging
- Microservices: Istio (Ingress, Egress, Kiali, mTLS), OpenAPI/Swagger
- Scala: Akka HTTP / Streams / Actors / FSM, Play Framework, http4s6 cats, cats-effect, doobie, elastic4s, refined, pureconfig
- Infrastructure: GCP, Terraform, Helm, CircleCI, Spinnaker, Grafana, Prometheus, Cloudflare
- Messaging: Kafka, RabbitMQ, Google Cloud PubSub
- Containers: Docker, Kubernetes, GKE
- Databases: Cloud SQL (PostgreSQL/MySQL)
- Search: Elasticsearch/ELK, BigQuery
- Android: SDK development with UI components (https://github.com/tranzzo/android-sdk)

Middle Software Engineer - BlackBerry

Jun 2016 - Aug 2017

Project

Joined the team as an intern. In a year I was able to become a Middle Software Engineer, completed two certifications: Java OCA & Java OCP. Participated in developing Secure Android SDK. Also worked on creating proxy for SOAP for running white-box integration tests on Jenkins. https://www.blackberry.com/us/en/products/blackberry-dynamics/platform

Client

BlackBerry Dynamics, Canadian client https://www.blackberry.com/

Responsibilities

- Developing secure Android application
- · Developing test tools for automated integration testing
- Administrating build system
- · Maintaining and supporting CI infrastructure

Achievements

- Wrote an HTTP proxy for SOAP backend for white-box testing purposes. This dramatically simplified automated test coverage.
- Created UI for interactive debug logs uploading
- Wrote hundreds of automated tests, including UI

Technology stack:

- Android (Java)
- Android Test Kit
- · Spring Web (MVC), Data
- Hibernate
- Groovy
- Bash
- Gradle Plugins